I spent the best part of last year
لقد قضيت أجمل أوقاتي من السنة الماضية
working on a documentary
وانا اعمل على فلم وثائقي
about my own happiness --
يتحدث عن سعادتي
trying to see
محاولاً ان ارى
if I can actually train my mind
ان كنت استطيع ان ادرب عقلي
in a particular way,
بصورة معينة
like I can train my body,
كما استطيع ان ادرب جسدي
so I can end up with an improved feeling
لكي استطيع ان اخرج بروح معنوية مرتفعة
of overall well-being.
ورضى تام عن حياتي
Then this January,
ثم في شهر يناير
my mother died,
توفيت والدتي
and pursuing a film like that
وكان اطلاق فلم كهذا
just seemed the last thing that was interesting to me.
كان آخر شيء يمكن ان افكر فيه
So in a very typical, silly designer fashion,
وبدوت كمصمم ازياء سخيف
after years worth of work,
لم يعد لديه شيء يذكر يقدمه بعد سنوات من العمل
pretty much all I have to show for it are the titles for the film.
وفي الحقيقة كل ما لدي الآن لكي أقدمه هو عروض الترويج لهذا الفلم
(Music)
(موسيقى)
They were still done
لقد تم تصوير هذه المشاهد
when I was on sabbatical with my company in Indonesia.
عندما كنت متفرغاً لشركتي في اندونيسيا
We can see the first part here was designed here by pigs.
كما ترون الجزء الاول استخدمت به الخنازير
It was a little bit too funky,
لقد كان مشهداً غريباً
and we wanted a more feminine point of view
وكنا نريد نقداً أُنثوياً في هذا الخصوص
and employed a duck
ومن ثم استخدمت البط
who did it in a much more fitting way --
والذي كان أكثر ملائمة
fashion.
على الاقل بصورة فنية
My studio in Bali
ان الاستديو الخاص بي في بالي
was only 10 minutes away from a monkey forest,
كان يبعد 10 دقائق عن غابة القردة
and monkeys, of course,
وحتماً القردة
are supposed to be the happiest of all animals.
يفترض انها الاكثر سعادة على كوكب الارض
So we trained them to be able to do three separate words,
لذا دربناهم من اجل ان يشكلوا هذه الحروف الثلاث المنفصلة
to lay out them properly.
لكي يشكلوها بصورة صحيحة
You can see,
كما ترون
there still is a little bit of a legibility problem there.
مازال هناك مشكلة تنسيق هنا
The serif is not really in place.
فبعض الحروف ليست في مكانها الصحيح
So of course, what you don't do properly yourself
حتماً .. اذا اردت ان تقوم بشيئاً بإتقان كما تريد ..
is never deemed done really.
فعليك ان تقوم به بنفسك
So this is us climbing onto the trees
و هنا نحن نتسلق الاشجار
and putting it up over the Sayan Valley
لكي نضع هذه حول وادي سيان
in Indonesia.
في اندونيسيا
In that year, what I did do a lot
وفي تلك السنة ... ما قمت به
was look at all sorts of surveys,
كثيراً هو الاطلاع على الكثير من الاستبيانات
looking at a lot of data on this subject.
والكثير من المعلومات فيما يخص هذا الموضوع - السعادة -
And it turns out
وقد تبين
that men and women
ان الذكور و الاناث
report very, very similar levels of happiness.
لديهم نفس المستوى من السعادة
This is a very quick overview
وهذا عرض سريع
of all the studies that I looked at.
لكل تلك الدراسات التي اطلعت عليها
That climate plays no role.
ان المناخ لا يلعب دوراً في تحديد مستوى السعادة
That if you live in the best climate,
اي ان كنت تعيش في مكان مناخه مميز جداً
in San Diego in the United States,
مثل سان ديغو في الولايات المتحدة الامريكية
or in the shittiest climate, in Buffalo, New York,
او في اسوء مناخ مثل بوفلو في ولاية نيو يورك
you are going to be just as happy
فانت ان كنت سعيداً في الاولى .. ستكون أيضاً ...
in either place.
في الثانية
If you make more than 50,000 bucks a year in the U.S.,
وان كان مدخولك اكثر من 50 الف دولار في السنة
any salary increase you're going to experience
فان اي زيادة في الراتب عن تلك
will have only a tiny, tiny influence
لن تؤثر الا تأثيراً بسيطاً جداً على مستوى سعادتك
on your overall well-being.
ورضاك العام عن حياتك
Black people are just as happy as white people are.
ايضاً البشرة .. فسود البشرة لديهم نفس مستوى سعادة بيض البشرة
If you're old or young
وان كنت يافعاً او متقدماً في السن ..
it doesn't really make a difference.
فهذا لن يضفي فرقاً
If you're ugly or if you're really, really good-looking
وان كنت قبيحاً او جميلاً
You will adapt to it and get used to it.
لانك سوف تتأقلم وتعتاد على ذلك
If you have manageable health problems
وان كنت تملك مشاكل صحية ( مقدور عليها )
it doesn't really matter.
فهذا لن يضفي فرقاً على مستوى السعادة ان لم تكن تملكها
Now this does matter.
ولكن ما يضفي فرقاً حقا على مستوى السعادة
So now the woman on the right
كما ترون بين المرأة على الجهة اليمنى
is actually much happier than the guy on the left --
والتي تبدو سعيدة اكثر من الشاب على الجهة اليسرى
meaning that, if you have a lot of friends,
بسبب انها تملك الكثير من الاصدقاء
and you have meaningful friendships,
بمعنى .. انه من يملك صداقات حقيقية
that does make a lot of difference.
فان ذلك يؤثر تأثيراً شديداً على مستوى سعادتك
As well as being married -- you are likely to be much happier
كما ان كون المرء متزوجاً يزيد من سعادته
than if you are single.
عن اذا ما كان عازباً
A fellow TED speaker, Jonathan Haidt,
احد اعضاء " تيد " جوناثان هايدت
came up with this beautiful little analogy
قال ذات يوم تحليل مميز
between the conscious and the unconscious mind.
يخص العقل الواعي و العقل الغير واعي
He says that the conscious mind is this tiny rider
قال ان العقل الواعي هو عبارة عن رجل صغير
on this giant elephant, the unconscious.
يجلس على فيل كبير والذي هو يمثل العقل الغير واعي
And the rider thinks
والسائق يظن
that he can tell the elephant what to do,
انه يستطيع ان يشير على الفيل ما يقوم به
but the elephant really has his own ideas.
ولكن الفيل لديه افكاره الخاصة ويقوم بما يحلو له
If I look at my own life,
وان نظرت الى حياتي
I'm born in 1962 in Austria.
فانا ولدت في النمسا عام 1962
If I would have been born a hundred years earlier,
و إن كنت قد ولدت قبل مئة عام من ذلك العام
the big decisions in my life would have been made for me --
فاني موقنٌ ان قراراتي الكبيرة .. كانت قد اتخذت بدون استشارتي
meaning I would have stayed in the town that I was born in;
اعني انني كنت حينها سأبقى في قريتي التي ولدت فيها
I would have very much likely
وربما سوف ادخل نفس
entered the same profession that my dad did;
النطاق الذي يعمل فيه والدي
and I would have very much likely married a woman
وربما سوف اتزوج امرأة
that my mom had selected.
تختارها لي والدتي
I, of course, and all of us,
.. انا . .و جميعنا اليوم
are very much in charge
مسؤولون عن معظم القرارات الكبيرة
of these big decisions in our lives.
التي تواجهنا في حياتنا
We live where we want to be --
فنحن نعيش في المكان الذي نريده
at least in the West.
على الاقل هذا الامر للغرب
We become what we really are interested in.
ومن ثم ندخل التخصص الذي يثير فضولنا
We choose our own profession,
ونختار وظائفنا
and we choose our own partners.
ونختار شُركائنا في الحياة
And so it's quite surprising
وهذا أمرٌ مُلهمٌ للكثير
that many of us
من الاشخاص في هذا العالم
let our unconscious influence those decisions
ونحن نترك بصورة ما " العقل اللاواعي " يؤثر على تلك القرارات
in ways that we are not quite aware of.
بصورة نحن لا نعيها بشكل مباشر
If you look at the statistics
وان نظرنا الى الاحصائيات
and you see that the guy called George,
فاننا سوف نرى .. ان من يدعى جورج على سبيل المثال . ..
when he decides on where he wants to live --
والذي لديه القرار في اختيار مكان اقامته ..
is it Florida or North Dakota? --
هل تظنون انه سوف يختار داكوتا .. ام فلوريدا ..
he goes and lives in Georgia.
حسناً .. .سيقطن على الاغلب في جورجيا
And if you look at a guy called Dennis,
وان نظرنا الى شخص يدعى دينيس ..
when he decides what to become --
والذي لديه القدرة على اخيار مجال عمله
is it a lawyer, or does he want to become a doctor
هل تظنون ان سيصبح محامياً ..
or a teacher? --
طبيباً .. مدرساً ..
best chance is that he wants to become a dentist.
انه على الاغلب سيغدو " طبيب اسنان " ( دينتست = طبيب اسنان )
And if Paula decides
وان احتارت بولا في من
should she marry Joe or Jack,
سوف تختاره شريكاً للحياة بين جوزيف او جاك
somehow Paul sounds the most interesting.
فهي حتماً ستنظر الى بول كشريك مثير للاهتمام اكثر
And so even if we make
اذا .. وان كنا نظن اننا على وعي وتحكم تام
those very important decisions
بخياراتنا المهمة في هذه الحياة
for very silly reasons,
فانه ولاسباب " ربما سخيفة "
it remains statistically true
فان الاحصائيات .. تبقى الحكم
that there are more Georges living in Georgia
فالعديد من جورج ينتقلون للعيش في جورجيا
and there are more Dennises becoming dentists
والعديد من دينيس .. يختارون طب الاسنان
and there are more Paulas who are married to Paul
وهناك عدد اكبر من بولا . .يرتبطون ب بول
than statistically viable.
وهذه الاحصائيات .. واقعية حقاً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now I, of course, thought,
طبعاً في بادىء الامر .. ظننت ان هذا الامر فقط ..
"Well this is American data,"
في الولايات المتحدة الامريكية
and I thought, "Well, those silly Americans.
وقلت لنفسي .. ان هؤلاء الامريكيون ..
They get influenced by things
دوماً يتأثرون .. بهذه الامور السخيفة
that they're not aware of.
التي لا يعونها ..
This is just completely ridiculous."
كم هذا مدعاة للسخرية
Then, of course, I looked at my mom and my dad --
ولكن عندما نظرت الى والدي و والدتي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Karolina and Karl,
كارولينا و كارل
and grandmom and granddad,
وجدي و جدتي
Josefine and Josef.
جوزيف و جوزيفين
So I am looking still for a Stephanie.
علمت انني لا محالة ك " ستيف " انني يجب ان اتزوج " ستيفاني "
I'll figure something out.
دعوني أعرض شيئاً آخر
If I make this whole thing a little bit more personal
سأحول المحادثة الى شخصية اكثر
and see what makes me happy as a designer,
انا كمصمم .. مالذي يجعلني سعيدا اكثر شيء ..
the easiest answer, of course,
ابسط اجابة هي لا شك
is do more of the stuff that I like to do
هو ان اقوم بما احب اكثر
and much less of the stuff that I don't like to do --
وان ابتعد عما لا احب اكثر
for which it would be helpful
وما يجعل هذا سلساً
to know what it is that I actually do like to do.
هو ما انا ماهر به في الحقيقة
I'm a big list maker,
كصانع " قوائم "
so I came up with a list.
لذا صنعت قائمة لسعادتي
One of them is to think without pressure.
على راس القائمة .. العمل بدون ضغط
This is a project we're working on right now
ان المشروع الذي نعمل عليه الآن
with a very healthy deadline.
وهو مشروع مفيد ..
It's a book on culture,
هو عبارة عن كتاب عن الثقافة
and, as you can see,
وكما ترون
culture is rapidly drifting around.
ان الثقافة تتأرجح بشدة هنا
Doing things like I'm doing right now --
2- السفر .. القيام بما اقوم به الآن
traveling to Cannes.
مثل السفر الى " كان "
The example I have here
هذا المثال هنا
is a chair that came out of the year in Bali --
هو كرسي انتج منذ عام في بالي
clearly influenced by local manufacturing and culture,
وهو يعبر عن ثقافة الحرفيين المحليين
not being stuck behind
الثالث - ان لا احكر نفسي
a single computer screen all day long
خلف الكمبيوتر طيلة النهار
and be here and there.
ان اجول واتعرف على المحيط
Quite consciously, design projects
الرابع .. ان اعمل على تصاميم فريدة بكل وعي
that need an incredible amount of various techniques,
والتي تحتاج العديد من التقنيات
just basically to fight
وان احارب
straightforward adaptation.
بصورة دائمة من اجل تبني قضايا هامة
Being close to the content --
وان اكون قريباً من " نطاق " مجتمعي
that's the content really is close to my heart.
والذي هو في الاساس يكمن في قلبي
This is a bus, or vehicle,
هذا باص .. او حافلة
for a charity, for an NGO
انها من عمل منظمة اجتماعية
that wants to double the education budget in the United States --
والتي تريد ان تضاعف الميزانية التعليمية في الولايات المتحدة الامريكية
carefully designed,
وقد صمم بصورة دقيقة
so, by two inches, it still clears highway overpasses.
وبهذا التصميم كان يعبر الطرق السريعة ويعبر عن الفكرة
Having end results -- things that come back from the printer well,
الامر الآخر .. هو ان احصل على نتائج .. ان اخرج بنتائج مميزة فعلاً ..
like this little business card for an animation company
هذا الكرت .. هو لشركة تصميم رسوم متحركة
called Sideshow
تدعى " سلايد شو " لوحة عرض
on lenticular foils.
مصنوع من رقائق عدسية
Working on projects
الامر الآخر .. العمل على مشاريع
that actually have visible impacts,
لها تأثير حقيقي في الاشخاص ..
like a book for a deceased German artist
مثل هذا الكتاب لفنان ألماني راحل
whose widow came to us
حيث قدمت الينا أرملته
with the requirement to make her late husband famous.
وقالت انها تريد ان تجعل زوجها الراحل مشهوراً ..
It just came out six months ago,
وهذا ما خرجنا به خلال ستة اشهر
and it's getting unbelievable traction right now in Germany.
وهو ينتشر بنطاق واسع في المانيا اليوم
And I think that his widow
واظن ان أرملته
is going to be very successful on her quest.
سوف تكون ناجحة جداً في تحقيق مبتغاها
And lately, to be involved in projects
و أخيراً .. ان انخرط في مشاريع مميزة
where I know about 50 percent of the project
حيث انا اعلم ان 50% من المشاريع
technique-wise
تدور حول الأسلوب/طريقة التنفيذ
and the other 50 percent would be new.
وال50% المتبقية .. يجب ان تكون جديدة
So in this case,
لذا في هذه الحالة ..
it's an outside projection for Singapore
نحن نعمل على مشروع في سنغافورة
on these giant Times Square-like screens.
في هذه الساحات الكبيرة لكي نحولها الى شاشات كبيرة
And I of course knew stuff, as a designer,
وانا اعرف فريقاً .. كمصمم
about typography,
مختصون بالطباعة
even though we worked with those animals not so successfully.
يستخدمون مهاراتهم مع هذه الحيوانات .. رغم عدم نجاحها تماماً ..
But I didn't quite know
ولم اكن اعلم كثيراً
all that much about movement or film.
عن تلك الحركة .. او الفلم
And from that point of view we turned it into a lovely project.
ومن ذلك الحين .. تحول عملهم .. فلمهم . الى مشروعي المفضل
But also because the content was very close.
لان هدفه كان قريباً جداً من هدفي ..
In this case, "Keeping a Diary
في هذه الحالة كنا ندفع في ان يكتب المرء مذكراته
Supports Personal Development" --
من اجل ان يدعم نموه الشخصي
I've been keeping a diary since I was 12.
وانا اكتب مذكراتي منذ كنت 12 عاماً
And I've found that it influenced my life and work
وقد وجدت ان هذا العمل هو " مُلهم حياتي "
in a very intriguing way.
بصورة متكاملة جداً
In this case also because
خاصة
it's part of one of the many sentiments
ان الجزء الاول منه - الفلم - مليء بالمشاعر
that we build the whole series on --
التي قمنا بتأسيس سلاسل عنها ..
that all the sentiments originally had come out of the diary.
المشاعر التي في الاساس خرجت من تلك المذكرات ..
Thank you so much.
شكراً جزيلا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)